Guide to the James T. Sears Papers, 1918-2011 and undated, bulk 1950-2004 RL.01162
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research and Writings, 1941-2007 and undated, bulk 1975-2005, 176 boxes
  - Major Works Subseries, 1941-2007 and undated, 104 boxes
    - Edwin and John: A Personal History of the American South (2009), 1919-2008 and undated, bulk 1937-1959, 5 boxes
      Files contain research materials and correspondence relating to a book chronicling a 40-year relationship between John Ziegler and Edwin Peacock, both of Charleston, S.C. Both men also served in the military during World War II. Includes photocopies of original correspondence (1941-1959) and a set of diaries (1937-1940) used in the 1993 book The Diary of Jeb and Dash, published by Farber and Farber. (The original full set of correspondence is held in the John Zeigler Papers at Duke.) Also includes oral interviews with John Ziegler conducted by Sears; research notes; printed materials on gay life in Charleston; materials related to southern women writers, including Carson McCullers, Edwin Peacock's longtime friend; photographs; and drafts and proofs. Audiovisual materials and electronic diskettes have been separated into the format-appropriate series. The personal papers of Edwin Peacock and John Zeigler are also held by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke.
      [Electronic files have been migrated to a library server. Please consult a reference archivist for access to these and other electronic files in this collection.]
      - Main Correspondence Files, 1941-2007
        - 13 folders (Box 177)
      - John Ziegler Correspondence, 1941-1959
        - 1941-1944 (Box 177)
        - 1944-1945 (Box 178)
        - 1945-1959 (Box 179)
      - "Jeb's" Diaries, 1937-1940, 5 folders
        - Diaries, 1937-1940 (Box 179)
      - Drafts and Proofs, 2007-2008, 5 folders
        - Files, 2007-2008 (Box 180)
      - Research Files, 1919-1996 and undated
        - Allen, Henry, 1919 (Box 181)
        - Notes, undated (Box 181)
        - McCullers, et al., 1996 (Box 181)
          [Contains photographic materials and 2 CD-Rs. Please contact Research Services for access to the electronic materials.]
          [Diskettes removed.]
        - Play based on Jeb and Dash, undated (Box 181)
        - John's poetry and writings, undated (Box 181)
        - Photographs, 1954-1995 (Box 181)
        - The Shako (Citadel newspaper) and Foothills, 1931-1940 (Box 181)
        - 1930-40 South, 1998 (Box 181)
        - Ninety-Nines, undated (Box 181)
        - St. Cecilia Society, undated (Box 181)
        - Murray, Pauli, 1938-1940 (Box 181)
        - McCullers, undated (Box 181)
        - Candlestick Murder, Charleston, 1958 (Box 181)
        - Walking Charleston, 2001 (Box 181)
        - Printed material, 1997-2004 (Box 181)
        - Southern Women, undated (Box 181)
        - Crompton, Louis, Homosexuals and the Death Penalty in Colonial America, 1976 (Box 181)
        - Charleston Red Light District, undated (Box 181)
        - Wilde's visit to the south, undated (Box 181)
        - Pre-20th century material, undated (Box 181)
        - Notes on Southern women writers, undated (Box 181)
        - Stein, Gertrude, visit to Charleston, 1981-1984 (Box 181)
        - The Shako (Citadel newspaper), 1934-1935 (Box 181)
  - Other Publications Subseries, 1984-2007
    Includes works edited by Sears, sometimes with other individuals; writings contributed by Sears to book-length works by others; many articles appearing in a variety of academic journals; and nine folders of book reviews. Includes Sears' 1984 doctoral dissertation on teacher education programs. Arranged in alphabetical order by title or topic of work; within, typically divided into subgroupings, including administrative files, correspondence, drafts and proofs, publicity, and research files, or, in some cases, arranged in some other original order as received. Many of these writings are also present in the form of electronic files.
    - Before Stonewall: Activists for Gay and Lesbian Rights in Historical Context, edited by Vern Bullough (2003), 1994-2003
      Chapters on activists Bob Basker, Hal Call, and Jack Nichols.
      - Article file (Box 182)
    - Beyond Zero Tolerance: Four Approaches to Integrating Lesbian/Gay Issues into Multicultural Education, 1995
      Article for AACTE book (American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education).
      - Article file (Box 182)
    - Book reviews by James Sears, 1991-2002, 9 folders
      - Book review files (Box 182)
    - Centering Culture: Teaching for Critical Sexual Literacy Using the Sexual Diversity Wheel (1997), in Journal of Moral Culture, Vol. 26, No. 3, 1995-1997, 2 folders
      - Article files (Box 182)
    - Columns by Sears, 1992-2001 and undated, 3 folders
      - Columns files (Box 182)
    - A Critical Ethnography of Teacher Education Programs at Indiana University (1984), 4 folders
      Sears' doctoral thesis.
      - Doctoral thesis files (Box 183)
    - Crossing Borders/Expanding Boundaries: Teaching, Thinking, and Theorizing About Sexualities Education, 1995
      - Article file (Box 183)
    - Cultural Wars in a Southern Town: Race and the Hidden Narrative of the Master, (2000) in Journal of Educational Policy, 2000
      - Article file (Box 183)
    - Curriculum, Cultures, and [Homo]Sexualities (1998), 1997-2003, 2 boxes
      Series edited by Sears. Arranged in two groups, Correspondence and Editorial Files, then alphabetically within each group.
      - Correspondence, 1998-2002, 9 folders (Box 183)
      - Editorial files, 1997-2003, 11 folders (Box 184)
      - Editorial files, 1997-2003, 2 folders (Box 185)
    - Curriculum, Religion, and Public Education: Conversations for an Enlarging Public Square (1998), 1993-1999 and undated, 3 boxes
      Edited by Sears with assistance from James C. Carper. Originated from controversy surrounding Sears' course on Christian fundamentalism and education (see other materials on this topic in the Teaching Series). Arranged in four groupings: Correspondence, Dialogues, Editorial Files, and Publicity. Correspondence includes letters written between Sears and chapter authors, and Sears and his publishers at Teachers College Press. Dialogues contain several printed round table discussions pertaining to chapters in this publication. Editorial files also contain correspondence with chapter authors and Teachers College Press, as well as chapters written by a select group of contributors. All files arranged alphabetically.
      - Correspondence, 1993-1996
        - Brantley, Paul, 1996 (Box 185)
        - Contacts, 1993-1994 (Box 185)
        - McLaren, Peter, 1996 (Box 185)
        - Provine, W., 1994-1995 (Box 185)
        - Public Agenda correspondence and evaluation, 1994 (Box 185)
        - Teachers College Press: correspondence and contracts, undated (Box 185)
      - Dialogues, 1994-1996
        - Conversationalists: Public Square, 1996 (Box 185)
        - Dinner dialogue: Textbooks, 1996 (Box 185)
        - End of book conversations drafts, 1996-1997 and undated, 7 folders (Box 185)
        - Outcomes-Based Education, 1995 (Box 185)
        - Teaching About Human Origins draft, 1995 (Box 185)
        - Teaching About Human Sexuality, 1995 (Box 185)
        - Values, 1996 (Box 185)
      - Editorial work, 1994-1997
        - Files, 23 folders (Box 186)
        - Files, 10 folders (Box 187)
      - Publicity, 1997-1999, 4 folders
        - Publicity folders (Box 187)
    - Curriculum Work as Public Moral Enterprise (2003), 2001-2003, 1 box
      Co-edited by James Sears and Rubin Gaztambibe-Fernandez. Contains correspondence and drafts and proofs.
      - Correspondence, 2001-2003, 6 folders (Box 188)
      - Drafts and proofs, 2002-2003, 9 folders (Box 188)
    - A Dangerous Knowing: Sexuality, Pedagogy and Popular Culture (1999), 1995-1999, 2 boxes
      Contains correspondence, editorial files, and administrative files. Correspondence includes letters to publishers, authors, and Debbie Epstein, Sears' co-editor. Editorial files also include correspondence with authors, as well as proofs and layouts. All files organized alphabetically.
      - Correspondence, 1996-1998
        - Cassell Academic, 1998 (Box 189)
        - Early correspondence, 1995 (Box 189)
        - Epstein, Debbie, 1996-1997 (Box 189)
        - Johnson, Richard, 1996 (Box 189)
        - Kruger, Andrew, 1996 (Box 189)
        - Rejections, 1996 (Box 189)
        - Salazar, Philippe-Joseph, 1996 (Box 189)
        - Steinberg, Deborah, 1996 (Box 189)
        - Wakefield, Nina, 1996 (Box 189)
        - Weeks, Jeff, 1996 (Box 189)
      - Editorial files, 1995-1999
        - Altman, Dennis, 1996-1997 (Box 189)
        - Beckett, Lori, 1997 (Box 189)
        - Burgess, Ian, 1995 (Box 189)
        - Connell, R. W., 1996-1997 (Box 189)
        - Crowley, Vicki, 1996-1997 (Box 189)
        - Crowther, Barbara, 1996-1997 (Box 189)
        - Dupuis, Martin, 1996 (Box 189)
        - Fine, Michelle, 1996-1997 (Box 189)
        - Original articles and chapters, 1998, 2 folders (Box 189)
        - Pallotta-Chianolli, Maria, 1996-1997 (Box 189)
        - Plante, Rebecca, 1996-1997 (Box 189)
        - Quinlivan, Kathleen, and Shane Town, 1997 (Box 189)
        - Sears, James, 1998 (Box 189)
        - Smyth, Lisa, 1997 (Box 189)
        - Thew, Neill, 1996 (Box 189)
        - Whatley, Marianne, 1995-1996 (Box 189)
        - Proofs, 1999, 2 folders (Box 190)
      - Administrative, 1996
        - Files, 3 folders (Box 190)
    - Democratic Curriculum Theory and Practice: Retrieving Public Spaces, 2000-2001, 2 boxes
      Publication of proceedings from the First Annual Curriculum and Pedagogy Conference in Austin, Texas, October 2000, edited by Sears and Kris Sloan and published in 2001.
      - Conference files, 2 folders (Box 190)
      - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 190)
      - Editorial files, 4 folders (Box 190)
      - Editorial files, 12 folders (Box 191)
    - Developing a Sense of Difference Among Gay and Lesbian Children in the Deep South: The Difference Between Being Queer and Being Different (1987), 1987
      Draft of paper presented at the Curriculum Theory Conference, Dayton, Ohio, 1987 Oct. 28-Nov. 1.
      - Draft of paper (Box 191)
    - Dictionary of Multicultural Education (1997), 1995-1996
      Two entries written by Sears on gay and lesbian studies and on homophobia and heterosexism.
      - Copy of two encyclopedia entries, 1995-1996 (Box 191)
    - Empathy, 1988-1995 and undated
      Contains files related to Sears' activities and responsibilities as editor of this journal for gay and lesbian studies and homophobia in education. Arranged into four groupings: Correspondence, Drafts and Proofs, Submissions, and Administrative Files. Correspondence files contain exchanges between Sears and publishers or authors. The Drafts and Proofs grouping also includes some correspondence. Submissions files include rejections, acceptances, and letters of intent to publish. A wide range of clippings, calls for papers, publicity, and assorted resource files are found in the Administrative grouping. Drafts and proofs are arranged in order received; all other sections are arranged alphabetically.
      - Correspondence, 1988-1994, 8 folders
        - Files (Box 191)
      - Correspondence, 1988-1994, 16 folders
        - Files (Box 192)
      - Drafts and proofs, 1988-1994, 9 folders
        - Files (Box 192)
      - Submissions, 1988-1994, 7 boxes
        - Files (Box 192-198)
      - Administrative Files, 1989-1994 and undated, 37 folders
        - Advertisements, 1990 (Box 198)
        - Annotations, 1989 (Box 198)
        - Assorted resources and printed material, 1990 (Box 198)
        - Blank copyright forms, undated (Box 198)
        - Blumenfeld, W. [no essay attached], 1993 (Box 198)
        - Call for papers, 1993 (Box 198)
        - Clippings, press releases, and printed material, 1990-1992 (Box 198)
        - Completed [Edition?], vol. 1 no. 2, 1989 (Box 198)
        - Copyright forms, signed, 1989 (Box 198)
        - Dali, 1990 (Box 198)
        - Denny, Ian, Curtis, 1994 (Box 198)
        - Fraken, D., Out of the Darkness (article reprint), 1991 (Box 198)
        - Galtz, L. (clipping), 1993 (Box 198)
        - Gwenwald photos, 1992 (Box 198)
        - Hardisty, J., Constructing Homophobia (article reprint), 1992 (Box 198)
        - Hochberg (article reprint), 1992 (Box 198)
        - June flyer, undated (Box 198)
        - Kramer, S., Fanning the Vision (article reprint), 1990 (Box 198)
        - Layout, vol. 2 no. 1, 1989-1990 (Box 198)
        - Mailing list, vol. 2 no. 1, 1990 (Box 198)
        - Manasse photos, 1992 (Box 198)
        - North American Man-Boy Love Association (NAMBLA), 1991 (Box 198)
        - Newsletter bid, 1990 (Box 198)
        - Pennington, S. (article reprint), 1995 (Box 198)
        - The Point; event lists; financial requirements, 1992 (Box 198)
        - Press releases, 1990 (Box 198)
        - Promotional statements, 1990 (Box 199)
        - Promotional statements (copies), 1990 (Box 199)
        - Quatrefoil library, 1991 (Box 199)
        - Reprints, The Ex-Gay Movement, 1990 April (Box 199)
        - Requests by others, 1989 (Box 199)
        - Resource section, undated (Box 199)
        - Ron [Orterew?] photos, undated (Box 199)
        - Sidebars, undated (Box 199)
        - Stroud, I., The Wilderness Generation (article reprint), 1992 (Box 199)
        - Tjabbes, Lesbians in Eastern Europe (pamphlet), 1990 (Box 199)
        - Vaughan [no submission attached], 1990 (Box 199)
    - From Margin to Center: On the 'Other' Side of the Curriculum Renaissance (2003), 1998-2002 and undated
      A review essay in Curriculum Inquiry, Issue 4, Vol. 33, of five works on curriculum development, with photocopies of the works included.
      - Review essay and copies of reviewed pieces (Box 199)
    - A Generational and Theoretical Analysis of Culture and Male (Homo)Sexuality (1998), 1997-1998 and undated, 2 folders
      - Files (Box 199)
    - Generational Influences on Contemporary Curriculum Thought (2000), Sears and J. Dan Marshall, in Journal of Curriculum Studies, Vol. 32 No. 2, 1999-2000
      - Article file (Box 199)
    - Greenwood Encyclopedia of Love, Courtship and Sexuality Through History, Volume 6: the Modern World (2008), ed. Sears, 2005-2007, 2 boxes
      Edited by Sears; hard bound copy has been transferred to the library's general collections and can be located through the Duke Library's online catalog.
      - Correspondence, 2005-2007, 43 folders
        - Files (Box 199)
      - Correspondence, 2005-2007, 41 folders
        - Files (Box 200)
      - Drafts and proofs
        - Introduction (Box 200)
        - Copyedited manuscript, 2007, 4 folders (Box 200)
      - Research files, 2007
        - Greenwood Press catalog (Box 200)
    - Growing Older: LGBT's in the New Millenium (2008), 2006-2007
      Files of contributor correspondence and publication agreements, and one folder of publisher correspondence, for double issue of Journal of Gay and Lesbian Social Studies published while Sears was editor. Hard-copy drafts of articles are not included, but electronic files of drafts have been mounted to the library server - please contact a research archivist for assistance in accessing these drafts. Arranged in original order as received.
      - "Growing Older" files (Box 201)
    - Handbooks for Teachers and Parents (2005-2007), 2004-2005
      Series edited by Sears for Greenwood Publishing Group. Includes the following titles: Including Children with Special Needs (2005), Holding Schools Accountable (2006), and Bullying (2007). Chiefly correspondence and administrative files. Organized as received.
      - "Teachers and Parents" files (Box 201)
    - Homophobic Bullying (2008), 2005-2007
      Contributor files of correspondence and publication agreements for double issue of Journal of Lesbian Gay and Bisexual and Transgender Social Work, published while Sears was editor. Drafts of articles are often included, and electronic files of most drafts have been mounted to the library server; please contact a research archivist for assistance in accessing electronic files. Arranged in original order as received.
      - "Bullying" files (Box 201)
    - Institutional Climate (1994), in Journal of Homosexuality, 3 boxes
      - Drafts and proofs, 2 folders (Box 202)
      - Research files (Box 202-204)
    - Journal of Gay and Lesbian Issues in Education (JGLIE), 2001-2005, 8 boxes
      Editorial files assembled by Sears during his tenure as editor for Volumes 4 and 5 (2006-2007). Contributor files found in the Publication Files grouping represent accepted manuscripts only. Beginning with Volume 5, the journal was renamed Journal of LGBT Youth, and published by Taylor and Francis.
      - Correspondence (Box 205)
      - Editorial files (Box 206)
      - Publication files (Box 207-212)
    - Laura Bragg and her 'Bright Young Things...' with Louise Allen, in Renaissance in Charleston: Art and Life in the Carolina Low Country, 1900-1940 (2003), 1997-2002 and undated, 7 folders
      Set of folders relating to an essay on Laura Bragg, a Charleston resident, museum director, library founder, and social progressive, entitled Museums, Friends and Lovers in the New South: Laura's Web, 1909-1931, (2000) with Louise Allen. The essay later became a chapter in the 2003 publication.
      - "Laura Bragg" files (Box 213)
    - Miscellaneous writings by Sears, 1970s-1995 and undated
      Fragments and full drafts of various articles, essays, and memoirs, mainly untitled.
      - Sears writings files (Box 213)
    - Out of Harmony on the Cherokee Boundary: Clinics, Culture and the Sex Ed Curriculum (2002), in Sex Education, Vol. 2 No. 2, 2001-2002
      - "Our of Harmony" files (Box 213)
    - Overcoming Heterosexism and Homophobia: Strategies that Work (1997), 1994-1998, 3 boxes
      Edited by Sears and Walter L. Williams. Arranged into three groups: Correspondence, Editorial Files, and Administrative Files. Correspondence files include letters written by Sears and contributors, and exchanges with the Columbia University Press. Chapters and topics edited by Sears and incorporated into his publication are found in the Editorial Files group; these folders are arranged by author's last name. Administrative files are routine in nature. All files are arranged alphabetically.
      - Correspondence, 1994-1997, 5 folders (Box 214)
      - Editorial Files, 1994-1995, 36 folders (Box 214-215)
      - Administrative Files, 1994-1998, 5 folders (Box 216)
    - Pedagogical Currents (1999), 1999
      Series published by Educator's International Press, for which Sears served as associate editor. One file mainly of correspondence.
      - Editorial files (Box 216)
    - Queer Community Studies (2001-), 1998-2003 and undated, 2 boxes
      Series published by Haworth Press for which Sears served as senior editor beginning in 2000. Files are arranged in two alphabetical groups, Correspondence and Editorial Files.
      - Correspondence, 1999-2003, 6 folders (Box 217)
      - Editorial files, 1998-2003 and undated, 9 folders (Box 217)
      - Editorial files, 1998-2003 and undated, 2 folders (Box 218)
    - Queering Elementary Education: Advancing the Dialogue About Sexualities and Schooling (1999), 1996-2000 and undated
      Edited by Sears and William James Letts IV. Organized into the following groupings: Correspondence, Drafts and Proofs, Editorial Files, Publicity, and Administrative Files. Drafts and Proofs folders contain layouts, publisher proofs, and copy edits; also included in this grouping are proofs of Sears' introductory chapter, Teaching Queerly: Some Elementary Propositions. All folders arranged alphabetically; editorial files by author's last name. Several earlier administrative and correspondence files refer to this publication as "Teaching Queerly" rather than by its final published title.
      - Correspondence, 1998-1999, 5 folders (Box 218)
      - Drafts and proofs, 1999, 4 folders (Box 218)
      - Drafts and proofs, 1999, 3 folders (Box 219)
      - Editorial files, 1998-1999, 13 folders (Box 219)
      - Editorial files, 1998-1999, 16 folders (Box 220)
      - Publicity, 1999-2000, 3 folders (Box 220)
      - Administrative files, 1996-1998 and undated, 5 folders (Box 220)
    - Race, Class, Gender and Sexuality in Pre-Stonewall Charleston (1997), chapter in Carryin' on in the Lesbian and Gay South, 1995-1997
      - Chapter file (Box 220)
    - Reader's Guide to Lesbian and Gay Studies (entry on U.S. South), 1998-1999
      - File with draft (Box 220)
    - Ron Lambe: Time in Camelot (1999), 1999
      Drafts of essay, possibly unpublished, on Running Water communal gathering, the Faery movement, and Lambe's life and role. Material later appears in Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones.
      - File of drafts (Box 220)
    - Sexuality and the Curriculum: The Politics and Practices of Sexuality Education (1992), 1989-1993 and undated, 6 boxes
      Edited by Sears. Arranged into groups of correspondence, editorial files, rejected abstracts, publicity, and routine administrative files. Correspondence includes letters written to authors and publishers at Teachers College Press. Abstracts, drafts, correspondence, and proofs by various authors are found in the editorial files. Administrative files include promotional statements, abstract reviews, and calls for papers.
      - Correspondence, 1989-1992, 11 folders
        - Files (Box 220)
      - Correspondence, 1989-1992, 2 folders
        - Files (Box 221)
      - Editorial files, 1989-1992 and undated
        - Brunner, Diane, 1990 (Box 221)
        - Burman, Louise and Diane Lee, 1989-1991, 2 folders (Box 221)
        - Carlson, Dennis, 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 221)
        - Draft, 1991, Folders 1-4 of 6 (Box 221)
        - Draft, 1991, Folders 5-6 of 6 (Box 222)
        - Earls, Ruth, Joanne Fraser, and Bambi Sumpter, 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 222)
        - Fine, Michelle and Lynn Phillips, 1991-1992 (Box 222)
        - Fonow, Mary Margaret, 1990 (Box 222)
        - Friend, Richard, 1990 (Box 222)
        - Goodman, Jesse and Maria Sapon-Shevin, 1990, 2 folders (Box 222)
        - Kimmel, Michael, 1989 (Box 223)
        - Klein, Susan, 1990-1992 (Box 223)
        - Koch, Patricia, 1990, 2 folders (Box 223)
        - Kupel, David, 1989 (Box 223)
        - LaCerva, Christine, 1990-1991, 3 folders (Box 223)
        - Linn, Eleanor, 1990-1991, 1 of 2 (Box 223)
        - Linn, Eleanor, 1990-1991, 2 of 2 (Box 223)
        - McLaren, Peter, 1991 (Box 223)
        - Miller, Jaye, 1990 (Box 224)
        - Niemiec, Richard, 1989-1990 (Box 224)
        - Sears, James T., Dilemmas and Possibilities of Sexuality Education: Reproducing the Body Politic, drafts, undated (Box 224)
        - Sears, James T., The Impact of Culture and Ideology on the Construction of Gender and Sexual Identities, drafts, undated (Box 224)
        - Shakeshaft, Carol, 1992 (Box 224)
        - Silin, Jonathan, 1991 (Box 224)
        - Sultana, Safia, 1989 (Box 224)
        - Thompson, Cooper, 1989-1990 (Box 224)
        - Trudell, Bonnie, 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 224)
        - Whatley, Mariamne, 1992 (Box 224)
        - Ward, Janie Victoria and Jill McLean Taylor, 1990-1991 (Box 224)
        - Whitson, James Anthony, 1991 (Box 224)
      - Publicity, 1992-1993, 3 folders
        - Files (Box 225)
      - Rejected abstracts, 1989, 13 folders
        - Files (Box 225)
      - Administrative files, 1989-1991, 9 folders
        - Files (Box 225)
    - Sexuality Education, in What Principals Should Know...: A Primer on School Subjects (2000), 1998-2000
      - File with article (Box 225)